[music]
>> Wallace Herndon Smith was a 20th century
American artist.
Born in the spring of 1901 and the first
of three children to Lyda and J. Herndon
Smith, [music]
the roots of Wally's family run deep in
the rich history of St. Louis, Missouri.
His mother Lyda's side of the family was
famously known for the philanthropic
work of her uncle,
>> [music]
>> Robert Brookings.
In the 1800s, Brookings' vision,
resources, and will established landmark
institutions.
Wally's father, J. Herndon, came to St.
Louis from Chicago in 1899.
>> [music]
>> He was a successful banker and president
of A.G. Edwards & Sons before becoming
the president of Smith, Moore & Company.
>> And then [music]
they put together a the Midwest Stock
Exchange, which was in St. Louis.
And
>> [music]
>> that was pretty big deal in those days.
Now then they took it as Chicago
surpassed St. Louis, they took it and
moved it. They went to Chicago.
>> Loved his father.
He referred to [music]
his father
to me anyway as good time Charlie. He
said dad would always trying [music] to
take him out and show him a good time
and let him have fun in life.
His mother [music] was more serious and
sort of uh uh
down-to-earth and [music]
she sort of kept him on the straight and
narrow, make sure he did his school work
[music] and stuff like that. She was a
little bit more of the
disciplinarian in the family.
>> My great-grandmother Lida was again,
very much very matriarchal and I think
ran a very tight ship.
>> And Wally would say, "You didn't cross
mom, but dad you get away with stuff."
>> And I can remember as [music] a small
child my grandmother saying, "Wallace."
She called him Wallace all the time.
"Wallace, there's a bit of a chill in
the air." And he'd go Oh.
groan
>> [laughter]
>> and head down for the coal shovel.
And you could hear him banging around
down there [music] like a some kind of a
wild animal. So, with the doors the the
furnace smashing and he groaning and
whatnot and mom always giggling
at his performance, [music] which was
part of the reason for it. He had a
built-in audience with sister Kate, as
he called her.
>> The family's future was secure and for
Wally, his education began at Smith
Academy, the Lawrenceville School in New
Jersey,
>> [music]
>> and ultimately Princeton, where the
renowned Triangle Club gave the young
artist a voice.
>> [music]
>> Wally entered Princeton in 1920.
These were highly productive and
successful days.
He was acting, writing, and composing
music. He was social and funny, always a
showman.
His stage work had created a buzz, and
to top it off, he was falling in love.
>> We met at a dance in Montclair.
I thought I was quite twinkle toes.
I put on some fancy steps that lured her
apparently, hence the pyramids, and here
we are today.
>> Mary Alice Kelsey was a student at
Vassar College. She was independent and
strong, focused, and stunning.
>> This was his freshman year in college,
and he was already quite a smash hit.
And I've always liked people who are
smash hits, so I pursued him. Because he
was this man who he wasn't a man. He was
all of 19 or 20, who was a big hit on
the stage. I was terribly impressed.
>> Mac dearest,
I hate to grow sentimental in writing
you this letter, but I absolutely cannot
help it.
There's no use in my beating around the
bush any longer, and I simply got to
express my feelings.
I think you're the sweetest, most
wonderful girl I've ever known.
But please don't laugh at me because I
really mean every word of it.
I was enraptured throughout the entire
[music] weekend, and I do nothing now
but sit around and think of you.
If you've ever been head over heels in
love yourself, then you know what an
irrational coma one is in,
>> [music]
>> and will be able to understand my
situation. This is no sudden affection
that has come over me.
The spark has been glowing for several
years, and it took only a flash of those
eyes to set it off.
>> Known throughout her life as Kels, she
gave Wally a sense of balance.
>> Kels was was always the calm kind of um
voice of reason in the house.
Uh
And as I said, Wally was all I just
remember him as being very
just very boisterous and you know,
really always just very energetic, and
and she was very just very calm and uh
very proper um in her mannerisms
certainly around me.
Whenever ever there was anything that
needed to be organized it was Kelce that
played that role.
>> In college, this was a long-distance and
long courtship sustained mostly through
written letters.
>> Mac dearest,
was extremely glad to get your letter
yesterday and to learn that all is well
at Vassar.
Now that the grind has started down
here,
I begin to wish it was still summer.
I suppose that's the way it always goes,
however.
I'm so damn busy with all the other
things that I haven't cracked a book
since I've been back.
Will probably be thrown out on my ear in
February.
I should like nothing better than to
take your sweet advice about
overworking, but now that I've started
this thing I've got to see it through.
It gets on one's nerves sitting in front
of a typewriter from morn till night,
but it won't be so very much longer now.
Just between the two of us,
the show looks good, but it may cost me
a diploma.
>> The show was a musical comedy called
Drake's Drum.
In 1923, the New York Times provided a
review.
In those days, the Ziegfeld Follies were
the premier variety show. Wally was
offered a gig with the Follies by
Ziegfeld himself.
Wally passed.
>> I was offered a job in the theater in
1930-something,
but Dad wouldn't let me take it or
didn't suggest that I take it.
>> Um Jimmy Stewart had said to him,
you know, that that he thought he could
make it.
>> Wally wrote the score for um
uh play called Ships that Ships that
Pass in the Night in Princeton. And and
and
he wrote music and words and music and
and he was an actor and here were people
that he had been associated who were
all over the screen and getting all kind
of recognition, you know, in movies and
and and and history books
uh uh and he I think sometimes he
thought hey, that could have been me.
>> 68 years later, 1 year after Wally's
death, the Princeton Alumni Weekly
listed key contributors in Triangle
history.
>> He had a taste of Broadway and he didn't
like it. He didn't like all the
machinations that went on behind the
scenes and the double-crossing.
He was too idealistic for that.
He had this other thing in mind. He
wanted to say what was in himself and
not the lines that somebody provided to
him. He wanted his own lines.
>> Wally decided to move away from theater.
>> I often wonder what it is to all this
art and bunk I spend my time with.
It may and probably does enrich our
lives to a certain extent by giving us a
little inward glow of [music]
satisfaction.
I get terribly fed up of it all and
often come to the conclusion that the
only real art is that of living quietly
in the country on ham and eggs. And then
I come to a passage of poetry like this
and I realize I'm wrong.
Oh, to build to build, that is the
noblest of all the arts.
Painting and sculpture are but images or
mere shadows cast by outward things on
stone or canvas having in themselves no
separate existence.
But architecture
existing in itself and not seeming as
something it is not surpasses them as
substance shadow.
>> After graduation, he enrolled in the
graduate architecture program at
Princeton.
>> [music]
>> It's hard to tell whether I'll be a good
architect as yet.
I'm still [music] rotten at the
mathematical part and hate it, but I've
overcome my sloppiness and developed a
pencil technique that amazes even me
myself.
>> Confident, yet struggling, this passage
from his letters provides insight.
>> I'm having a hell of a time with
architecture from one standpoint. I
can't be accurate.
Everything has to be done to the
fraction of an inch, and my pen always
skips or the ink blots, [music]
and I get frustrated as hell.
My houses are sometimes nice to look at,
but the main objection offered to them
is that it would be impossible to live
in.
I always forget fireplaces and furnaces.
>> In 1926, while he concluded several
years of courtship and married [music]
his beloved Kells.
>> His father said, "If you're going to be
an architect, you must [music] have the
best background possible."
So, we went and lived in Paris for a
year.
And all the time that he was supposed to
be studying architecture, he actually
[music] was doing watercolors.
That's what he actually wanted to be
doing.
>> Watercolors
occupy an interesting place in his body
of work, I think. Um in terms of
painting, watercolor was the first
activity that he really undertook
because he started out studying to be an
architect, and watercolor is used many
times by people studying architecture
and by architects
uh for um enhancing and um
uh filling in detail of uh architectural
drawings. A lot of times architectural
drawings will be
uh rendered in in pen or pencil or some
sort of graphic medium, and then the
watercolor washes will will give an
atmosphere and give a more uh a stronger
sense of space so that you can imagine
the architectural form uh through the
watercolor. So, this is the direction
that he came to watercolor. And I know
that, uh, he started out as a as a
watercolor painter and very early in the
1930s won a prize for his watercolors.
And so, I think that was a a signal to
him that he was moving in the right
direction. So, watercolor, I think,
again, occupies an important place in in
his career, although I think that he's
become better known for his for his
oils.
>> My father said to me when I first took
up painting, he was in the brokerage
business, so I wouldn't be here now. He
said to me, "Wallace, you do just what
you want. I'll give you a certain amount
of money and you work hard at it. I
insist on that. But, if you do,
something may come of it."
>> Wally photographed Paris and attended
classes at the École des Beaux-Arts to
advance his knowledge of watercolors.
>> We were very young.
We had very little money, but we did
scrape up enough money to buy a little
car with a two-horsepower or something.
And every weekend when I was done
pretending that I was doing work at the
bizarre where I did do some work, we
climb in there and go out into the
countryside.
And it was all so beautiful with the
orangey roofs and everything and just
take long trips and then come back to
Paris. It is the most beauty.
You can't describe the French
countryside.
>> Most notably during the Paris years was
the birth of their only child, Jay, in
1927.
>> I I often look back at their life and
their moving around and whatnot. And I'm
not sure there was too much planning
in any of it. Jay was born in Paris,
but, um,
you know, that was just
that point in time and then
and then they came back.
>> The sudden death of Wally's father, Jay,
in 1928 prompted their return to St.
Louis.
>> We hated to come back.
I think if Wally's father had not died,
we would probably have stayed over
there.
>> Wally and Kels returned to St. Louis
heavy-hearted and determined to build a
career.
Wally's family became his clients.
>> Wally was working for LaBoum and Klein
in the late 20s and they were one of the
leading fashionable architectural firms
in St. Louis during that period. Louis
LaBoum was also a member of St. Louis
society and
uh
was on the board of the St. Louis Art
Museum
uh and so he was uh
considered one of the leaders of the
profession in St. Louis. And he was a
eclectic architect and his although
people said he never lifted a pencil
himself, he had good designers on staff
and his partner Eugene Klein was a good
designer of pure various period revival
styles. So, the house that Wally
designed for his mother came right
[music] out of that tradition. It was
what we now sometimes call French
eclectic derived from the late 17th and
early 18th century houses of France,
which of course he loved anyway and
[music]
uh it's characterized by the very high
mansard roof and uh rounded door and uh
other features characteristic of French
houses of that period. But it it's one
of the best houses of this era, I would
say.
>> My grandmother owned the
first lot, the second lot, and the third
lot. She owned all the lots on one side
of that lane.
And um
Uncle Wally built his
own house
up there early on, which became the
Culvers' house.
And then he went on to New York, I
guess, and
you know, so he but Uncle Bob kept the
next lot. We had a victory garden there
in World War II and then Uncle Bob built
his house
and the bottom one
went to
you know, the youngest child, Mom.
>> The Smith family bought this property
off Price Road
in the
early '20s and it actually had space for
three very large houses.
This house was built by Wally for his
sister Taffy and it's one of his best
designs. It's a federal style with
beautiful fan lights over the door and
over the side.
The fine detailing of the windows you
can see with the hinged shutters again.
And the very massive chimney at the west
end of it. It sits very beautifully at
the top of a rise, but it's informal in
its massing
which was typical of the so-called
country club style of that era as
opposed to the kind of palatial houses
that were in the city.
>> I'd always take him to see the one on
Fielding Road, which his friend But
Culver lived in it that time.
That house since has been torn down. He
was very proud of that house and he
talked about how it had 12-in brick
walls and and how
solid what a solid foundation he made.
He was very proud of those two houses
and [music] we went to see them quite
often, maybe once a week.
>> While the couple lived in St. Louis,
Wally was transitioning from
architecture to painting.
>> Of course, there was wonderful Louis
LaBeaume, who was an architect. He used
to paint with him.
>> Louis LaBeaume was my closest friend. He
lived to be 89 years old. I worked for
him as an architect once and I painted
him standing in the same studio we've
just discussed against the light a few
years before he died. This painting is
is a little different and little earlier
than some of the others. Notice what I'm
after. Notice that I'm asked after for
gesture, the gesture gesture his hand,
the whole gesture of the body to make
the see things seem lifelike and real.
The color is muted, but I think it
expresses Louie as well as any portrait
expresses anybody that I've ever done.
>> And then, of course, dear Fred Conway.
They were very great friends.
Not that they paint exactly alike, but
they respected each other's way of
painting and respected each other as
painters.
They had a very painterly friendship.
They talked about painting a lot.
>> He and Fred Conway not only became
painting buddies, they became drinking
buddies.
And they'd always
uh as Wally [music] said, celebrate the
completion of a good piece of artwork
with a bottle of Scotch.
So, uh I think
Fred Conway and and and he painting
together
helped him
weather the storm here in St. Louis.
>> No, I don't think anyone in St. Louis
has understood him except for Fred
Conway and Louie LaBeaume.
Nobody else has really understood what
it means to be a painter, that you
dedicate your life to it.
>> They would get together
a bunch of them on about once a week
and paint.
Just for the camaraderie and the
stimulation and whatnot.
Zeke Pettus, Jane Pettus was in the
group, Louie LaBeaume, couple of others.
Um but I think the whole family really
endorsed that architecture.
Thing is a great way to go and when the
when the when the depression came and
there was no more work, you had to do
something else.
>> My father said, "If you take up
painting, you won't make a penny."
>> I thought he was a good painter. Well,
you [music] couldn't stop him anyway. He
was determined to paint and there was
absolutely no stopping him.
I must say that from the start, he was a
good painter.
>> Before moving to New York, Wally began
showing his artwork at the City Museum
and the Saint Louis Art Museum in 1932
and 1933.
>> Smith was coming at an interesting time
in the development of American art, a
peculiarly American art.
Um, he was at that transition point. He
was coming of age as a painter in that
transition point between regionalism and
this this style that emphasizes realism,
um, and the transition to abstract art,
which of course made New York the center
of the art world starting in the 1940s
and beyond.
And
Smith [music] was a sort of bridge,
timewise, chronologically,
>> [music]
>> between those two movements in American
art, the the realist movement and the
movement into, um, into abstraction.
>> New York helped strengthen Wally's
technique.
>> I remember Alexander Brook way back,
years ago. He said, "But Smitty, you
leave all your darks out.
You got to have dark pushing something
behind it out, or vice versa, in order
to get some vitality into the painting.
It mustn't be flat."
After I studied with Brook at the League
for some time, he said, "Smitty, you're
doing fine, getting along all right, but
you ought to change partners and study
at least for a little bit with somebody
else."
And I said, "Who do you suggest?" And he
said, "Thomas Benton."
And I said, "Oh, God, I don't crave his
work,
but I'll do it."
>> He was extremely well versed in theory.
He knew more about modern art than than,
uh, probably, [music]
um, any of his contemporaries. He he
went to Paris. He he went to museums. He
did his did his research.
Um
but very interestingly, he was just not
one to to change or to follow a trend or
a fashion. He stayed committed [music]
to his ideals and to
the
project [music]
of rendering form solidly
>> [music]
>> on the canvas and unifying it and making
it a um delightful uh composition to
behold.
>> It was here at the Art Students League
where Wally became friends with Jackson
Pollock.
>> Pollock tried to get Wally to come over
to the extreme abstract position where
he was
if I may dribbling paint and whatnot on
canvases and
and doing this and it was a big hit. It
became quite popular.
And
Jackson Pollock said, "Wally,
you got to come on over." He says, "This
is really really simple. They give you
all kinds of money for it and there are
booze and broads around and it's really
a good time. And you just got to do
this."
And Uncle Wally said,
"Jack, I just can't."
>> Influenced by European art and
architecture, Smith spent a lifetime
developing his craft guided by the
influence of Rembrandt, Goya, and
Matisse.
>> Remember the statement Matisse said, "I
want a picture that I can sit down in a
chair at the end of the day and even if
it's a Matisse or what it is, it can
help me and help me relax."
That's Matisse.
That's what I wanted.
I didn't get it the way he did, but
that's what I wanted.
I wanted that simplicity.
>> He was
really really interested in um modernist
artists, particularly [music] French
modernist artists.
Um, he loved Matisse.
As much as he was interested in some of
the French modernist painters, he never
went [music] as far as they did in terms
of experimentation with color and with
the loosening up of form.
>> You don't like to say it cuz you don't
want people to think you're a
know-it-all.
So many friends turned to abstraction
painting only.
And who am I to tell somebody how to
paint? I'm just a different jib, as we
say in sailing. It's not made for me.
I have a simpler, straightforward way.
>> It may be one of the reasons why Wally
Smith is not better known because he
continued on in this realist style
starting in the 1930s and then all the
way through, um, throughout his career,
and he never became interested in, in
radical abstract experimentation.
So, he was slightly out of fashion at
the time in American art, which is not
to say that he was not a great artist. I
think in many ways his dedication to his
craft makes him stand out among
any of the realist painters of the 20th
century in the United States. I have
never seen a body of work that
represented such steadfast commitment to
the kinds of, uh, artistic ideals that
he was interested in.
>> Although Wally worked for Alexander
Brook, his greater friendship was with
Peggy Bacon, especially after 1940 when
Brook and Bacon divorced. And in 1939,
Peggy Bacon enticed Wally to join her as
an instructor at the Tyler School of
Fine Arts in Philadelphia.
>> Wally was never a part really of the art
world.
Those four years at Princeton really
kept him from being a part of the art
world in New York.
They were important years when they were
all just starting and painting.
Alex Brook, McFee, Hopper.
>> I think it's very interesting that
Smith's experience in New York wasn't
all that productive. He didn't really
fit in among uh the artists even in the
1930s and 40s, even among artists who
were doing work
>> [music]
>> that you could compare to Smith's.
>> We didn't know enough about New York in
the beginning. So, he started at a
school uptown.
We really should have been downtown. As
it was, we were neither fish nor fowl.
We were halfway.
>> There was a general idea throughout the
19th and 20th centuries that great art
comes from struggle.
Artists like Van Gogh serve as the
model, poor, despairing, unpopular.
This extends to American artists in the
1930s, 1940s when artistic expressionism
was prioritized.
And the idea [music] was that artists
had more to express if they were facing
greater challenges.
>> He had the the privilege of being able
to,
you know,
travel the world and
paint,
you know, in in places and
things that um
you know, the average person
you know, the average artist in New York
would not have been able to do. They
they would not have been able to,
you know, hop on a ship and
go live in Paris or, you know, travel
Europe and do the things that he did. Um
uh so, I think that absolutely it
influenced it had to have influenced his
his work that he did. And I think
probably from a um personal standpoint,
he had that
that comfort knowing that financially um
things were taken care of.
>> Don't think that you can um that you can
just attribute Smith's um
commitment to his art to the fact that
he didn't have to work for a living
otherwise.
I really don't know of another painter
who stayed so single-minded and so
consistent to his
um to his style and to his interests
than Smith. Um
I think that he would have produced the
same kinds of paintings regardless of
the background that he came from,
regardless of how much he had to
struggle or how little he had to
struggle to to support himself.
>> No, it was never easy for him. In fact,
people have said to me, "What [music] a
wonderful thing to have such a hobby as
being able to paint like this."
But it's never been a hobby. It's been
his lifeblood. [music]
It's the same as a woman having a baby
who conceives it. She goes through the
period of gestation, and then she
produces it. And the whole thing is very
painful. And all of it is very painful.
All of these pictures, I don't think
they show the pain behind them.
>> He was a a very controlled disciplined
kind of painter. I like to think of him
as the most workman-like painter I
I know of. He did studies, he took
photographs, he devoted himself to the
visual world and rendering it. He did
nothing offhandedly or um
or or quickly or without the utmost
consideration for its for its structure
and its weight. Um he was just a very
deliberate painter and and [music] very
very serious, and someone one that I
admire for that for that reason.
>> He has a good sense of design. There's a
good sense of layout with Wally's
paintings. There's a logic to them.
There's a There's a coherent
composition.
He knows what goes where on the on the
page as it were. And he also has a very
very good sense of when a painting is
done.
One of the problems in my opinion that
so many artists have is they put too
much information on the page. They don't
know when they artwork is finished.
Wally has an unerring sense of when the
painting is finished. And I think people
respond to that. There's a wonderful
logic and a coherence in Wally's work.
>> Well, it's always hurt him a lot because
he realizes that people think that he's
playing.
It's true. He's always laughed about his
pictures and made fun of them.
But that was a protective covering
due to the fact that people have made so
much fun of his pictures and of him
painting.
So that he reacted and made fun of them
himself.
But that was only a protective covering
because when people would stab at his
paintings,
it was as if they had kicked him
upstairs.
>> Wally would ultimately exhibit over a
dozen times in New York City.
A lift of confidence came one evening
from renowned artist Edward Hopper.
>> Well, Mr. Hopper, you know, was the sort
of quintessential
poor struggling artist that became
hugely successful.
But Edward Hopper came in and a kind of
a hush fell over the place and he climbs
up the stairs and whatnot and Uncle
Wally sort of runs to greet him. They
weren't It didn't come across as being
on a first name basis. It was Mr.
Hopper.
And he was older, of course, and
but [clears throat] he came in
and they had about four rooms on the
third floor or something in the Ren
gallery. Mr. Uh
uh Hopper went around and he would study
the paintings and go to the next room
and he would go all the way around
without really making any kind of a
remark at all.
And when he got to the end of it with
Uncle Wally right behind him the whole
way,
he turned to him and he said,
"Not bad, Smith. Not bad."
I I thought about that phrase many
times, "Not bad." It it
It's It's a pretty nice recommendation
coming from Edward Hopper.
>> I thought that was an interesting
sidelight that he could have been, if he
had been a little bit earlier, he would
have been accepted more.
I think the fact that he was a college
graduate, too, also kept him away from
the mainstream. After all, a different
level of education, I think a broader
point of view probably as a result.
>> As the threat of war loomed on the
horizon,
Wally's brother, Robert, urged a return
to St. Louis.
During the war, Wally almost immediately
began exhibiting at the City Museum and
the St. Louis Art Museum.
>> After the war, we stayed in St. Louis
and I thought it was too bad that we
didn't go back to New York.
But Wally pointed out the fact that he
was really better off in St. Louis
because he was without influence from
fellow painters. He wasn't under the
pressure that he was in New York.
And also, Wally has this other side, you
see. He's a nervous actor.
He can pull over a song if he's
accompanied.
He can put over a song as well as
anybody I've ever heard on stage.
>> I mean, uh
every opportunity that you can possibly
imagine he turned into a production
par excellence, which was just fun for
everybody.
>> He was an outdoorsman.
He loved golf,
hunting,
tennis,
and fishing.
>> So, my grandmother was always very
uh probably over overly protective of of
me. So, I think she was always a little
worried anytime I'd get in the brown
Torino with Wally and take off. Um
and one one summer, I don't I don't
I don't remember how old I was. I was
probably
I don't know, maybe 10 or 11. Uh so, we
were in the boat. We had these little
rowboats in the trout pond and he was up
there
casting and hooked me behind the ear and
and on the
swing out, literally almost threw me out
of the boat. And um you know, so I
yelled and I probably cried a little bit
and he got the got the hook out of my
ear and um driving back, he probably
said three or four times, "Don't you
tell your grandmother that this happened
because if you do, we're never going
fishing again."
>> Wally and Kells cherished time with
friends.
>> Pulitzer was awfully good to him.
The exposure that he got, you know, in
the rotogravure and the Sunday Sunday
papers and whatnot, plus the friendship
that they had.
Um
they would go hunting down in Arkansas.
Uh on numerous occasions, they'd get on
Joe's DC-3
and away they'd go.
And they'd shoot ducks or they would
wind up Sometimes I can remember he
would be in Florida.
And
Uncle Wally said,
"We stopped in Atlanta on the way back.
It was such a long trip, we had to get
gas. So, I thought the least I could do
was uh
was was fill up
the tanks.
So, I said to the pilot, 'Hey, this
one's on me.' And the pilot said,
You give me $640.
Uncle Wally said, "I'm sorry I even
brought it up."
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, they had good times. And Joe
Pulitzer was a
was a Uncle Wally promoter.
And uh
you know, the family bought that
portrait self-portrait of Uncle Wally
for $10,000
way back when.
>> And that's the strange thing because I
painted that in almost an effortless
way, just in the north light.
I stood there and my legs felt pretty
good that day, and I painted away for 4
or 5 hours, and I knew that I had the
structure then.
Above which I put any little details
which I wanted, but there weren't many.
And I worked on that for only about 4 or
5 hours.
I sold it for a good, good price,
unexpectedly. A 47 by 36 canvas.
It was so ridiculous.
I didn't make any gestures. I just
looked myself,
which makes me begin to wonder what I do
look like.
>> Wally didn't get a rise out of
portraits.
>> My things didn't look or feel like the
people I was painting, and they wanted
them that way.
Pretty girls wanted to be roughed up and
dashed up and look a little fancier, but
I didn't have that desire.
>> Instead, he moved toward familiar
landscapes.
>> [music]
>> For years, we've had a home up at Harbor
Springs, Michigan, which is up near the
Canadian border.
It's a beautiful spot. We live in a old
house that mother left to us, looking
down over the lake, surrounded pine
trees. Down below, I have a studio in
the woods, which we built in the days
when I was an architect.
I am naturally, having been there for
some 50 or 60 years,
observed the lake, all inhabitants, the
little town which is full of Indians,
but I have observed particularly the
mood of the lake.
The lake is different from the ocean. It
is quiet. I often think when I wake up
in the morning of Indians in their old
birch bark canoes paddling around the
lake and of the campfires that went on
in those days.
However, those days are gone and now I
paint the lake for its moods have hardly
changed. There's still the old Indian
church there by the lake surrounded with
the dark trees.
>> And it was the one
constant, if you will, in his life. It's
just it's a beautiful place
and very conducive to um to to painting.
I mean, there's a lot and his work
reflects that. A lot of beautiful things
to paint. Uh he again loved the water.
Um we talked he loved sailing and so a
lot of his his art is are sailing
scenes, water scenes.
Um
So yeah, I I think that um
you know, that was a was, uh you know, a
huge part.
Um huge influence.
>> There's something about being in contact
with the elements out on the sea and
particularly in a race where the water
is splashing all over you and everything
and you wonder where it all came from.
>> He represents this area in a way that
is so palatable to me. There are other
people who paint here now and
most of it's too cute for me.
I don't I don't like cute.
This is uh
this is deep and real to me.
So.
>> Here I sit at the old table in the glass
room overlooking the water just as I
used to a year ago.
It's really the most beautiful spot
imaginable, especially at sundown,
when I can look far across the water and
see the faint blush of the west mellow
all the coming darkness.
Not a sound except the lazy lapping of
the water on the shore
and the faint whistle sailing away to a
haven under the hill.
The pine trees around the cottage rise
heavenwards
like the slow curling smoke from a dying
campfire.
>> I know that
Harbor Springs was a place where he
really
uh I think he he really would go to
refresh himself and go to refresh his
his ideas and um and to take maybe a
little bit of a break from painting and
to entertain friends and um you can you
can see how much of his life and how
much of his own energy and his own
interests are rooted in in this place by
his sailboat paintings.
>> Practically all of my work has been done
here.
We're going way back.
And if you examine the work more
carefully, you'll see that most of it's
pictures of sailboats and the water
around here.
It's also interesting to notice that I
made some progress in this line.
Having worked on it for so many years, I
kind of feel like I'm on a boat at
times.
>> A lot of his inspiration came to Harbor
Springs cuz a lot of scenes of
waterscapes or landscapes or scenes from
his house in Harbor Springs, you know,
or a house that his mother bought.
Why he liked Harbor Springs, he thought
it was an inspiration to him. He loved
to take
his easels and his his his paints and
his brushes and when he could,
you know, walk around or drive around
the countryside and find places to
paint. He was very well liked up there
in in years ago and he'd tell me about
how socially he just blended in. He was
always a the life of the party, you
know, more or less in in at the parties
in Harbor Springs.
>> I think they had a pretty good time up
here because he had an audience here. He
had week with town singing in Harbor
Springs with originally smattering of
St. Louis people, but then they you
know, they began they they knew people
from
from all over the place and uh
and and and he sold
some paintings to some friends
and admirers, too.
>> It just captured the essence of this
place. It was real.
It wasn't so perfect.
Um
it has great depth. It has a great
emotion.
But it has the beauty of the town.
And the town is a beautiful place
with beautiful people in it.
Uh the church
has a serenity about it.
It's a place I love to go, that
particular church. Um
and it's it's just
you know, had everything.
>> Wally painted for nearly 60 years.
Moonlight Sail is a staple in Smith's
collection.
>> Now here we have something that's
different. Here's a different mood of
the lake.
Here's a simple a very simple
composition with a sailboat headed out
into the moonlight
and very little in it itself, but it has
a mood of quiet. How would How could you
paint a moonlight sail other than that?
It's the quiet pervasiveness of the
scene that I think makes it important.
Every inch of the canvas is adjusted.
The moon, I trust, is in exactly the
right place. It's been moved several
times. The simple canvas extends high
into the painting. The color is [music]
extremely restricted and low in key. On
the other hand, I feel there's a great
sense of color because to me color,
which is the most important thing in a
painting, is not necessarily a matter of
colors,
but of various areas. I think this
painting shows that perhaps as well as
any other that I have.
>> More often than not, he's got really
dynamic lines in his sailing scenes.
This one for example, this
this is a beautiful scene that is uh
a vertical format with horizontal bands
of the sky and the land and the and the
sea and yet right in the middle of it
he's he's sort of knife-like dropped
this um this mast which just cuts right
through with a diagonal and really just
shifts the entire
energy of the entire canvas.
>> After the war, Wylie and Kelsey resumed
their long duration travels in France.
Wylie found inspiration seen in scores
of personal photographs and sketches.
He visited museums and continued to
study his art.
The highest exposure came in 1953 at a
show in Paris.
>> Paris bought a picture of mine called
snow in Clayton.
I took 35 pictures over that I did a
couple of days before we went on the
boat. It was of my studio in the snow.
And they were all so surprised. But they
don't see as much snow as we do. To know
how it feels.
>> And especially something's a scene so
hometown as you said, something a scene
right outside of his studio window
making making its way back to France.
You know, the place where he goes to to
study and to be inspired and and to look
at uh small towns and and just you know,
just incidental everyday scenes in
France. That's so inspirational to him
and for his own everyday scene, a scene
of you know, something that he sees all
the time out his studio window to have
traveled in the other direction. That
must have been so so thrilling.
>> [music]
>> When it became too difficult, he was it
was sad because
um
that was his life, you know, and uh
he would complain about his
his eyesight, you know, was was bad and
that he couldn't hold a brush or
something like that. It it it was kind
of sad because it it took away
a lot of time that, you know, [music]
where the time that he spent painting,
he would then now spend
uh
just sitting or watching television or
something like that. Uh
it was truly sad and and um
I guess that's how really I guess it was
it was [music] sad situation.
>> One of the things we used to do once a
week, we'd go to the um
the art museum.
And, you know, even in with feeling
memory and feeling mind
if Wally saw a piece of work by a
a Monet or a Matisse or or a Manet
from across the room, he could tell you
what that was.
>> Wallace Herndon Smith died in the winter
of 1990.
>> You know, to me he was
just
you know,
Wally and he was going to always be
there, you know, and [music]
uh so I think I'd go with my kids down
to the Lake of the Ozarks for some dance
competition they were having and I got a
call
uh at the hotel. I thought no one else
knows I'm here and I said nobody and it
was one of the nurses said, "You better
come back." Uh
you know, Wallace Smith just died, you
know.
It was a sudden death of Wally to me,
you know, cuz you know, I was used to us
hanging out
uh
three times a week or or or or just
driving around. He just like getting the
car and drive around sometimes. So, and
to for him to die while I was out of
town, then you know, and then he was
gone. So, uh
it wasn't like a long sickness or that.
He just got a cold that developed into
pneumonia and then he passed away.
>> [snorts]
>> I don't know how important
recognition from for his art was.
I think he did it um
cuz he enjoyed it and I know that um
you know, the way he interacted with
people, he liked
he liked to be around people that were
fun and were laughing and having a good
time. He liked to have a good time.
And uh so, I think
you know, he probably would want people
to remember him that way.
>> Artists don't really very often get to
be famous during their lifetimes. You
some for whatever reasons, there has to
be a passage of time for people to come
in and kind of reevaluate it.
>> Boy, he he he sort of covered the
waterfront there. He got a lot of
canvases out there.
Um
I mean, he stayed true to his
principles.
And whether or not that satisfied him or
not, I really can't
can't say.
>> [music]
>> He's never deviated from his goal that
he had, which was to express what he had
to, what was in himself.
>> [music]
>> And he shunned that when people said he
was a fool to have given that up. Going
on Broadway, you would have been a great
success. Now look what you do. Just
paint.
You could have been a successful man.
You're just nothing but an artist now.
>> Uh
I think that he
before he died, he felt that he was
beginning to get some recognition as an
artist. And then that made him happy.
>> Well, he those that own him love him
and don't want to give him up, which is
probably why he's not well-known.
Um because there hasn't been anything
that's come on the market for sale
in auction. [music]
Um if you are lucky enough to have a
Wally Smith, I don't want to give it up.
And my children have fallen in love with
them, too.
Um
they're very special. But if it can just
bring the
joy to other people that it's been
[music] brought to me,
then that's wonderful.
And perhaps he could be
really important because he
he's uh
so good at what he does.
Was so good at what he did.
>> Uh if if history is going to going to go
back and and sort of right a wrong, I
think it's going to go back and and
notice that through all of the other
fashions that that came and went in the
20th century in [music] in the history
of American painting, um
Smith never strayed from his course. And
he he just remained a very very very
solid, very um
very passionate [music]
um
very passionate painter. And I have to
imagine that history is going to
eventually give him give him his due. I
hope so, anyway. [music] He's He's
really an extraordinary painter, I
think.
>> Wallace Herndon Smith was a 20th century
artist. Period.
Whether he was acting,
writing plays, or composing music,
designing and sketching houses,
taking photographs, or painting
watercolors and oils, he remained
consistently
an artist.
>> Uh
I mean I
This is just me. It's taken my me my
life to find out what color I wanted.
It's taken me my life. I have not gone
jumped like Don Quixote jumped on a
horse and galloped off in all
directions. I've stuck to one way.
To what extent it's good or not, we
never seem to know in our own lives.
>> A
phantom ship drifting [music] on the
sea,
>> [singing]
>> lost in shadows, sailing [singing]
silently.
Though the grayness gather,
let on clouds [singing] be cloud her.
May
my dream ship
come again
to me.
All
the ships
that pass in [singing] the
>> [music]
>> night
far and lands out [singing] of sight,
like maidens,
we have known
>> [singing and music]
>> soon vanish
to be seen no
>> [music]
>> Bow
and smile,
then fade in the darkness. [singing]
Angels of light,
>> [singing]
>> say